<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!--
Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
distributed with this work for additional information
regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
"License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
software distributed under the License is distributed on an
"AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
specific language governing permissions and limitations
under the License.
-->
<document>
  
  <properties>
    <title>Status reports for the Apache Board</title>
    <author email="uima-dev@incubator.apache.org"> UIMA Documentation Team</author>
  </properties>
  
  <body>
    <section name="Apache UIMA Status Reports">
      <br />
            <subsection name="January, 2007">
        <!-- required: one-line summary (see http://incubator.apache.org/guides/ppmc.html)-->
        <p>UIMA is a component framework for the analysis of unstructured content such as
          text, audio and video.</p>
        <!-- required: date of entry into the incubator (see http://incubator.apache.org/guides/ppmc.html)-->
        <p>UIMA was accepted for incubation on October 10, 2006</p>
        <!-- required: top 3 items to resolve before graduation (see http://incubator.apache.org/guides/ppmc.html)-->
        <p>Top 3 things to resolve before graduation</p>
        <ol>
          <li>Complete code transition to Apache, do a release with all IP issues cleared</li>
          <li>Attract diverse, active committers</li>
          <li>Do a migration tool to enable migration to the Apache version</li>
        </ol>
    
            
        <!--
    *  Is there anything that the Incubator PMC or ASF Board specifically needs to address?
    * Are there any legal, infrastructure, cross-project or personal issues that need to be addressed?  
    *   (Are there any stumbling blocks that impede the podling?)
    * Check that the project's Incubation Status file up to date. (Also provide the URL.) 
    * What has been done (releases, milestones, etc.) since the last report?
    * What are the plans and expectations for the next period?
    * Are there any recommendations for how incubation could run more smoothly for you?
    * etc. (your own thoughts on what is important would be helpful!)

          -->
        
        <p>UIMA's incubation status file is here: <a href="http://incubator.apache.org/projects/uima.html">
        http://incubator.apache.org/projects/uima.html</a></p>

        <p>Some recent activity:</p>
        
        <ul>
          <li>The UIMA Sandbox has been populated with some example annotators</li>
          <li>A person new to the project, Jörn Kottmann, has written an Eclipse plugin
            he wants to contribute - we're going through the steps to bring this into the
            UIMA Sandbox.  He has submitted a software grant, and we're awaiting it's acknowledgement
            (as of Wednesday, Jan 10)</li>
        </ul>
 
        <p>We expect to do a release next month, and have been working to get all the little details needed
        for this completed.</p>       
        
        <p>We expect that we will need some assistance in doing our first release, 
          to verify we're following the rules properly.  We will 
        start by using our mentors, and then ask the incubator PMC to review the proposed release.</p>

      </subsection>
      
      <subsection name="December, 2006">
        <p>UIMA is a component framework for the analysis of unstructured content such as
          text, audio and video.</p>
        
        <p>Things are proceeding well, there is a lot of activity on the dev list, a lot of
          coding activity. We're pretty much settled in with the Apache infrastructure,
          have figured out how we want to use Jira in conjunction with SVN etc.</p>
        
        <p>Some recent activity:</p>
        
        <ul>
          <li>Infrastructure setup complete, barring some minor JIRA admin issues</li>
          <li>Website in good shape now, using Anakia</li>
          <li>Settled on Confluence for Wiki</li>
          <li>M2 build done</li>
          <li>Documentation has been converted to DocBook, although there are still some
            formatting issues to address</li>
          <li>Sample code has been updated</li>
          <li>Moving known issues from previous issue tracking systems to Jira</li>
          <li>Created sandbox as a place to contribute UIMA analysis components,
            tooling</li>
          <li> We've posted messages at the previous UIMA download locations notifying our
            user base that development has moved to the ASF incubator</li>
        </ul>
        
        <p>Our priorities for the coming weeks:</p>
        
        <ul>
          <li>We are hoping to be able to do our first Apache incubator release early next
            year. There is a lot of work to be done to make that happen, and we're still in the
            process of figuring out what that work is exactly ;-)</li>
          <li>Get the sandbox off to a running start</li>
          <li>Discuss ways to attract new committers</li>
        </ul>
      </subsection>
      
      <subsection name="November, 2006">
        
        <p>Accepted into the Incubator 10/06.</p>
        
        <p>UIMA is a component framework for the analysis of unstructured content such as
          text, audio and video.</p>
        
        <p>There was some discussion on incubator-general about changing the name of the
          project to something that's not an acronym and does not have a history outside of
          Apache. The final consensus though was that the arguments for keeping the name
          outweighed the ones for changing, so we're sticking with it.</p>
        
        <p>After the naming discussion was settled, we started getting the infrastructure
          set up:</p>
        
        <ul>
          <li>Mailing lists set up</li>
          <li>SVN repository created</li>
          <li>Apache, SVN, Jira accounts for committers (mostly done)</li>
          <li>Initial code drop checked in after receipt of software grant, Apache license
            headers inserted</li>
          <li>Initial version of website created</li>
        </ul>
        
        <p>Our priorities for the next few weeks:</p>
        
        <ul>
          <li>Finish infrastructure set up, get settled in with Apache</li>
          <li>Work on our (maven2) build</li>
          <li>Work on our website, document our build etc.</li>
          <li>Start directing our existing user base to Apache to attract some early
            adopters</li>
          <li>Discuss ways to attract new committers</li>
        </ul>
      </subsection>

      
   </section>
  </body>
</document>