<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!--
Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
distributed with this work for additional information
regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
 to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
"License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

  http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
software distributed under the License is distributed on an
"AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
specific language governing permissions and limitations
under the License.
-->
<document>

<properties>
<title>Apache UIMA Contribution Policy</title>
    <author email="dev@uima.apache.org"> Apache UIMA Documentation
      Team</author>
</properties>

<body>

<section name="Apache UIMA Contribution Policy">

        <h3 align="center"><font color="#FF0000"><b>Note: This is a working draft document.</b>
        </font></h3>
      <p align="center">Discussion of this document is occuring on the uima-dev mailing list.</p><br />
<p>
The Apache UIMA&#0153; Contribution Policy is summarized below: 
</p>

<ul>
<li>
  We are working to ensure that we have broad participation from the community, 
  at all experience levels and interests, but at the same time we are working to 
  minimize any risks to the ASF, the project and our community due to 
  inappropriate contributions of the intellectual property of others.
</li>
<li>
   We adhere to the standard Apache process and contribution agreements.
</li>
<li>
  We require every contributor to fill out the standard Apache
  <a href="http://www.apache.org/licenses/#clas">Individual 
    Contributors License Agreement</a>.
  <ul><li><p><b>Exception</b> - very small contributions such as fixing spelling errors, where the content
  is small enough to not be considered intellectual property, can be submitted by a contributor
  as a patch, without an ICLA on file for that contributor.  The contributor must check the the 
  box on the patch submission form granting the ASF rights to the contribution under the Apache 2.0
  license.</p>
  <p>The purpose of this exception is to lower the barrier for new contributors to make contributions.</p></li></ul>
</li>
</ul>

<subsection name="Strict Limits on Committer Contributions">

<p>
Committers can commit contributions to the repositories 
that they personally created <i>specifically for contribution to Apache UIMA.</i>
This is the standard stream of fresh original work, small enhancements 
and patches that are the normal flow of project life.
</p>
  
  <p>Committers can commit contributions to the repositories that
  were created by another contributor that do not have commit access,
  and were created <i>specifically for contribution to Apache UIMA</i>,
    provided: </p>
  <ul>
    <li>the contributor has a signed Contributors License Agreement
    listed with Apache
    
</li>
    <li>the contribution is made as an attachement to a UIMA Jira issue</li>
    <li>the attachment is marked as "ASF Granted License", indicating that
    the contributer has granted a license for the attachment sufficient to enable
    the UIMA Project to incorporate the attachement and distribute the result 
    under the Apache 2.0 license</li>
   
  </ul>
  
  <!--  
  <p>Committers can commit bulk code if they 
  adhere to these rules:
  </p>
  
  <ul>
    <li>All contributed code must be the original work of the contributor, or
      if the contributed code contains third party code not the original work of the
      contributor, it must be first discussed on the uima-dev discussion list and
      the IP Clearance process described in 
      <a href="http://incubator.apache.org/ip-clearance/index.html">
        Intellectual property clearance</a>
      must be done and documented.  A special subdirectory of the UIMA project is
    kept for storing the results of these clearances.</li>
      
    <li>The contributor must have an Apache Individual Contributor License Agreement
    recorded and acknowledged by the ASF.</li>
  </ul>
    -->

<p>
The purpose of 
this rule is to explicitly prohibit re-purposed "bulk" code 
<!-- that the contributor believes is their original work--> from being
added to the codebase without explicit oversight and acceptance. 
We can still accept contributions like that, but will track them explicitly
as Bulk Contributions.
</p>


</subsection>


<subsection name="Policy for Committers">

<p>
Each committer is required to complete a standard 
<a href="http://www.apache.org/licenses/#clas">Apache Individual Contributor License Agreement</a>.
This document asserts that the contributor is licensing their 
material to the ASF under the Apache license and is their original work (there's some other details).
This document is maintained and managed by the Secretary of the Apache Software Foundation.
</p>

<p>
We encourage every committer, if appropriate, to have their employer execute a 
<a href="http://www.apache.org/licenses/">Apache Corporate Contributor License Agreement</a>.
Note that this is recommended, but not required.
</p>

</subsection>

<subsection name="Policy for Bulk Contributions">

<p>
Any software or other contribution that was not created explicitly for 
Apache UIMA <i>in</i> the Apache UIMA project is considered to
be a 'Bulk Contribution'.  This status is independent of the purpose
or author of said contribution.  For example:
</p>

<ul>
<li> Personal utilities that a committer always uses on projects</li>
<li> Code from other open source projects that have a compatible license</li>
<li> Code from proprietary projects for which the donor has clear title</li>
<li> Larger pieces of Code being committed on behalf of other contributors, typically using a Software Grant</li>
</ul>

<p>
Any Bulk Contribution:
</p>

<ol>
<li> Will be donated via the project bug tracking system (JIRA) as a contribution under the Apache License.</li>
<li> Will be accompanied by a Software Grant (for large contributions) or ICLA (small contributions) 
  which will be registered with the Apache Incubator</li>
<li> done using a Software Grant will be registered in the Apache UIMA Bulk Contribution Repository
      via a <a href="bulk-contribution-checklist.html">Bulk Contribution Checklist</a></li>
</ol>

<p>
The Bulk Contribution Repository is a separate place in our administrative SVN in which records
  the Bulk Contribution Checklist and other checklist information, for each contribution.
We do this to
ensure that we have a clear and unambiguous record of any repurposed software that was contributed or
brought into the project source tree. 
</p>

<p>
We strongly urge any potential contributor to carefully examine their candidate for contribution (for instance,
  run code scans to insure the contributed code doesn't accidentally contain things that could
  cause licensing difficulties) 
before offering to the project.  To that end, we have started collecting information on tools and
other aids to help in this process, and it can be found on this page about 
  <a href="code-scan-tools.html">code scan tools</a>.
</p>

 
</subsection>


</section>
</body>
</document>