<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!--
 Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
 or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
 distributed with this work for additional information
 regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
 to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
 "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
 with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
 
 https://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 
 Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
 software distributed under the License is distributed on an
 "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
 KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
 specific language governing permissions and limitations
 under the License.
-->

<document>

 <properties>
  <title>Getting Started: Why Apache UIMA</title>
  <author email="dev@uima.apache.org">
   Apache UIMA Documentation Team
  </author>
 </properties>

 <body>
  <section name="Getting Started: Why UIMA">
   <p>
	 The "Getting Started: Why UIMA" guide should help you to understand what UIMA&#0153; is, 
	 what it can be used for, and how you can use it.
   </p>

  <subsection name="What Is UIMA">

   <p>
    UIMA stands for Unstructured Information Management Architecture and is a component 
    architecture and software framework implementation for the analysis of unstructured 
    content like text, video and audio data. Unstructured information represents the largest, 
    most current and fastest growing source of information available to businesses and governments.
   </p>
   <p>
	The motivation to develop such a framework was to build a common platform for unstructured analytics, 
	to foster reuse of analysis components and to reduce duplication of analysis development. 
	The pluggable architecture of UIMA allows to easily plug-in your own analysis components and 
	combine them together with others. A full analysis task of a solution using unstructured analytics 
	like search or government intelligence applications is often not a 
	monolithic thing but a multi-stage process where different modules need to build on each other 
	to get a powerful analysis chain. In some cases also annotators from different specialized vendors 
	may need to work together to produce the results needed. 
    The UIMA application interested in such analysis results does not need to know the details of how annotators 
    work together to create the results. The UIMA framework take care of the integration and orchestration 
    of multiple annotators.
   </p>
   <p>
	So the major goal of UIMA is to transform unstructured information to structured 
	information by orchestrating analysis engines to detect entities or relations and thus to build the 
	bridge between the unstructured and the structured world.
   </p>
   <p>
     <table width="100%"><tr><td align="center" valign="middle">
       <img src="./images/getting-started/analytics-world.jpg" alt="analytics world" border="0"/>
     </td></tr></table>
   </p>
   <p>
	The Apache UIMA project provides two Apache licensed UIMA framework implementations, 
	one for Java and one for C++.
   </p>

	</subsection>
  
   <subsection name="What Can UIMA Be Used For">
   <p>
	 UIMA is, by itself, an empty framework. Its purpose is to enable a world-wide, diverse community to develop
	 inter-operable, often complex analytic components, and allow them to be combined and run together, with
	 framework supplied scaled-out and remoting as needed. Some of the major external UIMA resources are linked
	 on the Apache UIMA website "<a href="external-resources.html">UIMA Resources on the Web</a>".
	 You can also check the <a href="sandbox.html">UIMA Addons and Sandbox</a> for components that can be used and combined 
	 to build your own application.
   </p>
   <p>
	 There are lots of use cases where UIMA may be applicable. One of the major ones are search applications. 
	 Within search applications, the unstructured content that is available mainly as text in various kinds 
	 must be processed and analyzed to be searchable. To obtain a powerful search application, the text 
	 content must be analyzed to get the document language followed by language dependent linguistic 
	 processing such as tokenization, lemmatization and part of speech detection. After these steps a 
	 more sophisticated analysis like entity detection and relation detection between entities can be done. 
	 For all these analysis steps UIMA and UIMA components can be used.
   </p>
   <p>
     Another important use case is business or government intelligence. For example, UIMA analysis is used 
     to extract structured information from car repair reports.  This data is then used for quality feed-back 
     and problem early warning systems.
   </p>
   <p>
     Other possible solutions where UIMA can be used for are the analsyis of call center notes to detect product 
     problems and customer issues or a public image monitoring solution to find out how others for example in internet
     forums or press releases think about my product or company.
   </p>
  </subsection>
 
  </section>
 
  

 </body>

</document>

