<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!--
	Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
	or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
	distributed with this work for additional information
	regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
	to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
	"License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
	with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
	
	http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
	
	Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
	software distributed under the License is distributed on an
	"AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
	KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
	specific language governing permissions and limitations
	under the License.
-->

<document>

	<properties>
		<title>Getting Started: Java UIMA Framework and SDK</title>
		<author email="dev@uima.apache.org">
			UIMA Documentation Team
		</author>
	</properties>

	<body>
		<section
			name="Getting Started: Installing the Java UIMA Framework and SDK, and Running Examples">
			<p>
				This
				guide helps you install the Java UIMA SDK release
				package and shows you how run the UIMA analysis example
				using some of the UIMA tooling.
			</p>

			<subsection name="Install UIMA SDK">
				<p>
					To get started with UIMA, you first have to install
					the Apache UIMA Java SDK release package. The packages are
					available at the UIMA
					<a href="downloads.cgi">download page</a>
					in different data formats for different platforms.
					Choose for example the .zip packages when you work
					on Windows or the .tar.gz packages when you work on
					Linux. Further we have two different package types,
					the binary distribution that contains the complied
					sources with script files to run the tooling and the
					source distribution that only contains the sources
					of the release.
				</p>
        
        <p>The package you want to download and install is the
          core Java SDK pacakge.  (Other packages include additional
          annotators and tools, and an Asynchronous Scaleout
          package enabling deployment of UIMA configurations using
          clusters of machines, for higher performance.)</p>
				<p>
					To install the core UIMA SDK you have to:
					<ol>

						<li>
							Download the perferred binary distribution
							package. To verify the download you can use the
							signature files provided for each file. For details on
							how to verify the download please refer to
							"<a href="downloads.cgi#VerifyDownload">Verifying a Release Download</a>"
						</li>
						<li>
							Unzip the downloaded release package to a target directory of your
							choice.
						</li>
						<li>
							Create an UIMA_HOME environment variable
							that points to the target directory where
							you have unzipped the downloaded release package.
						</li>
						<li>
							If you haven't already set a JAVA_HOME
							variable, create a JAVA_HOME environment
							variable that points to a JDK (Java
							Development Kit) of your choice. UIMA
							requires at least a Java level 1.5 to run.
							For more details about the supported Java
							versions, please refer to the README
							document of the release package.
						</li>
						<br></br>
						<li>
							Optional: If you want to have the UIMA
							script files in the PATH environment
							variable of your system you additionally
							have to add $UIMA_HOME/bin (or for Windows
							%UIMA_HOME%\bin) to your PATH settings.
						</li>
						<li>
							Optional: To use the provided examples you
							have to adjust the examples to your UIMA
							installation directory. To do that, just run
							the
							<code>adjustExamplePaths.sh</code>
							(or for Windows .bat) script in the
							<code>bin</code>
							subdirectory of your UIMA installation.
						</li>
					</ol>
				</p>
				<p>
					Now the installation of UIMA is finished and all the
					tooling and the examples should work properly.
				</p>
			</subsection>

			<subsection name="Running The UIMA Analysis Example">
				<p>
					UIMA comes with many examples for the different UIMA
					components and artifacts that can be created. All
					these examples are explained and used in the UIMA
					documentation when the specific components or
					artifacts are introduced. The UIMA analysis example
					that we want to use now is a combination of some of
					these example components that shows a basic document
					analysis using UIMA.
				</p>
				<p>
					To run the UIMA analysis example, we use the UIMA
					DocumentAnalyzer tooling that comes with the UIMA
					SDK. The tool can run UIMA analysis components (also
					know as annotators) on a given set of text documents
					and shows the result of the analysis run at the end.
				</p>
				<p>
					To start the UIMA DocumentAnalyzer, start the
					<code>documentAnalyzer.sh</code>
					(or for Windows .bat) file located in the
					<code>bin</code>
					subdirectory of your UIMA installation. The
					DocumentAnalyzer window pops up where the following
					values must be set to run the UIMA analysis example:
				</p>
				<p>
					Input Directory:
					<code>&lt;UIMA_HOME>/examples/data</code>
					<br></br>
					Output Directory:
					<code>&lt;UIMA_HOME>/examples/data/processed</code>
					<br></br>
					AE XML Descriptor:
					<code>
						&lt;UIMA_HOME>/examples/descriptors/analysis_engine/UIMA_Analysis_Example.xml
					</code>
					<br></br>
				</p>
				<p>
					Replace &lt;UIMA_HOME> above with the path of your
					Apache UIMA installation directory. In the sample
					screenshot below, the Apache UIMA installation
					directory was "C:\programme\apache-uima".
				</p>
				<p>
					<table width="100%">
						<tr>
							<td align="center" valign="middle">
								<img
									src="./images/getting-started/run_config.jpg"
									alt="DocumentAnalyzer run configuration" border="0" />
							</td>
						</tr>
					</table>
				</p>
				<p>
					To analyze the doccuments, click the "Run" button,
					which should, after a brief pause, pop up an
					"Analyzed Results" window.
				</p>
				<p>
					<table width="100%">
						<tr>
							<td align="center" valign="middle">
								<img
									src="./images/getting-started/analyzed_docs.jpg"
									alt="Analyzed Documents view" border="0" />
							</td>
						</tr>
					</table>
				</p>
				<p>
					To display the analysis results for one of the
					documents, just double-click the desired document.
					The important one for the UIMA analysis example is
					the Apache_UIMA.xmi file. When you open this
					document from the result list, you will see
					different kind of annotations such as:
				</p>
				<p>
					<ul>
						<li>EmailAddress annotations</li>
						<li>Name annotations</li>
						<li>PersonTitle annotations</li>
						<li>Sentence annotations</li>
						<li>Token annotations</li>
					</ul>
				</p>
				<p>
					When selecting the check-box for those annotations
					the highlighting in the text for those annotations
					can be turned on or off.
				</p>
				<p>
					<table width="100%">
						<tr>
							<td align="center" valign="middle">
								<img
									src="./images/getting-started/annotations.jpg"
									alt="DocumentAnalyzer annotation view" border="0" />
							</td>
						</tr>
					</table>
				</p>
				<p>
					This concludes the exercise. You may wish to
					experiment by submitting text of your own for
					analysis. To do that you can use the
					DocumentAnalyzer in the interactive mode. Just click
					the "Interactive" button instead of the "Run" button
					when you have entered the settings for the analysis
					example as seen in the screenshot above.
				</p>
				<p>
					After clicking the "Interactive" button to following
					screen is displayed where you can enter your text.
				</p>
				<p>
					<table width="100%">
						<tr>
							<td align="center" valign="middle">
								<img
									src="./images/getting-started/interactive.jpg"
									alt="DocumentAnalyzer interactive mode" border="0" />
							</td>
						</tr>
					</table>
				</p>
				<p>
					When clicking the "Analyze" button your text will be
					analyzed and you will see the analysis results in
					the annotation view in the same way as for the
					example above.
				</p>
			</subsection>
		</section>



	</body>

</document>

