<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!--
Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
distributed with this work for additional information
regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
 to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
"License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

  https://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
software distributed under the License is distributed on an
"AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
specific language governing permissions and limitations
under the License.
-->
<document>
<properties>
<title>Downloads</title>
<author email="dev@uima.apache.org">
 Apache UIMA Documentation Team</author>
</properties>
<meta name="robots" content="noindex" />
<body>

<section name="Downloading Apache UIMA&#0153;">
  <subsection name="Using via Maven dependency">
    <p>
      Most people use Apache UIMA through the artifacts we distribute on Maven Central. A dependency
      on the Apache UIMA Java SDK Core artifact looks like this:
    </p>
    <code><pre>
&lt;dependency>
  &lt;groupId>org.apache.uima&lt;/groupId>
  &lt;artifactId>uimaj-core&lt;/artifactId>
  &lt;version>3.2.0&lt;/version>
&lt;/dependency></pre></code>
    <p>
      Here you can find an <a href="https://search.maven.org/search?q=g:org.apache.uima">
      overview of all the artifacts on Maven Central</a>.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection name="Eclipse Tooling Update Site">
    <p>
    <a href="https://downloads.apache.org/uima/eclipse-update-site-v3/">https://downloads.apache.org/uima/eclipse-update-site-v3/</a>.
    </p>
    <p>
    If you're doing this for the first time, you may wish to consult the much more verbose
    instructions on the <a href="documentation.html">UIMA Documentation page</a>.
    </p>
  </subsection>
  
 
  <subsection name="Release packages incl. documentation and examples">
    <p>
      You are currently using <b>[preferred]</b>.  If you encounter a problem with this mirror, please
      select another mirror. If all mirrors are failing, there are <i>backup</i> mirrors (at the end
      of the mirrors list) that should be available.
    </p>
      
    <form action="[location]" method="get" id="SelectMirror">
      Other mirrors: <select name="Preferred">
      [if-any http]
        [for http]<option value="[http]">[http]</option>[end]
      [end]
      [if-any ftp]
        [for ftp]<option value="[ftp]">[ftp]</option>[end]
      [end]
      [if-any backup]
        [for backup]<option value="[backup]">[backup] (backup)</option>[end]
      [end]
      </select>
      <input type="submit" value="Change" />
    </form>
  
    <p>
      Use the links below to download Apache UIMA from one of our mirrors.  It is good practice to
      <a href="[location]#VerifyDownload">verify the integrity</a> of the distribution files, using 
      the signatures and checksums listed below in square brackets as asc, md5, or sha1.
    </p>
  
    <p>
      Apache UIMA is distributed as source and binary (ready-to-use) packages. These are available in
      <code>zip</code>, <code>tar.gz</code> and sometimes, <code>tar.bz2</code> archive formats. 
      Please note that the <code>tar.*</code> archives contain file names longer than 100 characters
      and have been created using GNU tar extensions. Thus they must be untarred with a GNU compatible
      version of <code>tar</code>.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection name="Apache UIMA v3">
    <insertDownloads version="uimaj"/>
  </subsection>
</section> 

<section name="Older Releases">
  <subsection name="Changes between Apache UIMA v2 and v3">
    <p>
      UIMA Java SDK, V3, is a re-implementation of the core Java version. It represents Feature 
      Structures as Java Objects, allowing them to be Garbage Collected, for example. It depends on
      and exploits many Java 8 features.
    </p>
    
    <p>
      The JCas implementation changed, and JCas classes (if used) will need to be migrated. The V3
      users guide describes a migration tool to aid in this process.
    </p>
    
    <p>There are many new features, described in 
      <a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="https://uima.apache.org/d/uimaj-3.2.0/version_3_users_guide.html#_uv3.overview.new">
      this overview</a>.  For more details, please see the documentation for version 3, which can be found 
      <a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="https://uima.apache.org/d/uimaj-3.2.0/version_3_users_guide.html">here.</a>
      Changes since the beta version are listed in the 
      <a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="../d/uimaj-3.2.0/RELEASE_NOTES.html">Release Notes</a>.
    </p>
    
    <p>
      Version 3 also has updated Eclipse plugin tooling, available at 
      <a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="https://downloads.apache.org/uima/eclipse-update-site-v3">
      https://downloads.apache.org/uima/eclipse-update-site-v3</a>.  
      This site's version of the JCasGen plugin will generate V3 JCas classes. You should only
      install one of either version 2 or version 3 Eclipse plugin tooling, into a single Eclipse
      installation. Should you wish to work with both, just create multiple Eclipse installations.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection name="Apache UIMA v2">
    <insertDownloads version="uimaj-v2"/>
  </subsection>
  
  <subsection name="Apache UIMA Asynchronous Scaleout v2">
    <insertDownloads version="2.10.3"/>
  </subsection>

  <subsection name="Apache UIMA Addons v2">
    <insertDownloads version="2.3.1"/>
  </subsection>
  
  <!-- includes latest uima-c++ release -->
  <subsection name="Apache UIMA C++ SDK v2">
    <insertDownloads version="2.4.0"/>
  </subsection>
  
  <subsection name="Apache UIMA Eclipse Tooling Update Site v2">
    <a href="https://downloads.apache.org/uima/eclipse-update-site/">https://downloads.apache.org/uima/eclipse-update-site/</a>.
  </subsection>
</section>
  
<section name="Archived Releases">
  
  <p>Older releases of Apache UIMA artifacts can be found 
    <a href="https://archive.apache.org/dist/uima">here</a>.  We highly
    recommend to not use those releases but upgrade to UIMA's <a
    href="[location]#Latest Official Releases">latest</a> release.</p>

  <p>Older update sites for UIMA Eclipse tooling are at Apache's archive for releases, and you can find links to them 
  <a href="eclipse-update-archives.html">here</a>.
  </p>
</section>

<section name="Verifying a Release Download" id="VerifyDownload">

<subsection name="Signature Files">
  <p>
  You may be wondering what those <code>.asc</code>, <code>.md5</code> and <code>.sha1</code> files
  on the download pages are good for.  They are signature files that let you verify the integrity
  and origin of the distribution artifacts (zip files, compressed archives) that you have downloaded.
  The signatures come in two varieties.  The <code>.md5</code> and <code>.sha1</code> files contain
  MD5 and SHA1 checksums, respectively.  The main purpose of those files is to let you verify the
  integrity of your release artifact.  You can use a tool to generate the same kind of checksum and
  check that it's the same checksum as the one you downloaded.  If the checksums agree, you can be sure
  that your archive did not get corrupted during transmission.
  </p>
  
  <p>
  The <code>.asc</code> files are so-called detached, ASCII-armored PGP signatures.  They let you do
  the same thing as the MD5 and SHA1 signatures, but they let you do something in addition: you can
  use these signatures to verify that the release artifacts were signed by a certain, trusted source. 
  The <code>.asc</code> files contain checksums that were encrypted with the private PGP key of the
  release manager responsible for the release.  This is useful if you received the release files from
  some arbitrary source, and you would like to be sure that what you have there is really a UIMA
  release (and not something containing a virus, for example).  You can then download the corresponding
  public key from a trusted source, and use it to verify not only the integrity of the file, but that
  it is actually the file the release manager signed in the first place.  Anybody can tamper with
  a released file and create a new checksum, but they can't fake the <code>.asc</code> file so it
  will work with the public key of the release manager.
  </p>
  
  <p>
  If you would like to verify your UIMA distribution or not is up to you, but unless you do it, you cannot
    be sure that you have an uncorrupted copy.  The next section will
  tell you how can use each type of signature file.
  </p>
  
</subsection>

<subsection name="Using GnuPG to Verify Release Files">

  <p>
  Start by downloading and installing <a href="https://www.gnupg.org/download/">GnuPG</a>, an 
  implementation of <a href="https://openpgp.org/">OpenPGP</a>.  There are many tools for verifying
  MD5 and SHA1 checksums, here's the GnuPG way for MD5:
  </p>
  <blockquote> <code>gpg --print-md MD5 &lt;ReleaseFile></code> </blockquote>
  <p>and for SHA1:</p>
  <blockquote> <code>gpg --print-md SHA1 &lt;ReleaseFile></code> </blockquote>
  <p>You can simply compare the resulting checksum to the one contained in the <code>&lt;ReleaseFile>.md5</code>
  or <code>&lt;ReleaseFile>.sha1</code> checksum file.  Use diff or your eyes, the signatures are short.
  </p>
  
  <p>A better way of verifying a distribution file is to use the PGP signature provided in the
  <code>.asc</code> files.  To be able to use the PGP signature files, you need to obtain the UIMA
  developers' public keys from a trusted source.  The keys do come with the distribution as well,
  but obviously using those is not a good way to ascertain the pedigree of a distribution.  Instead,
  get the keys from the main Apache distribution site (not a mirror), or 
  directly out of the UIMA SVN repository.
  </p>
    <dl><dt /><dd>(Right click the following links, and select save link/target as ...)</dd></dl>
    <ul>
      <li><a href="https://downloads.apache.org/uima/KEYS">KEYS from Apache main distribution site</a></li>
      <li><a href="https://svn.apache.org/repos/asf/uima/site/trunk/uima-website/docs/KEYS">
        KEYS from the main UIMA SVN repository using https security</a>
      </li>
    </ul>    
  
  <p>Depending how sure you want to be that those
  keys are really the ones you can trust, you may think of even safer ways to obtain them (for example,
  go to ApacheCon and get them personally).
  </p>

  <p>
  Once you have downloaded the <code>KEYS</code> file, you can import it into your GnuPG key registry
  with <blockquote> <code>gpg --import KEYS</code> </blockquote>
  Check what your key registry contains with 
  <blockquote> <code>gpg --list-keys</code> </blockquote>
  </p>
  
  <p>
  To verify a release file, <code>cd</code> to the directory with the release and run
  <blockquote> <code>gpg --verify &lt;fileName>.asc</code> </blockquote>
  for each file you would like to verify.  The output should contain something like this:
  <blockquote> <code>gpg: Good signature from "Thilo Goetz (CODE SIGNING KEY) &lt;twgoetz@apache.org>"</code> </blockquote>
  </p>
</subsection>

  <subsection name="Verifying MD5 checksums">
    <p>To verify an MD5 checksum, after downloading an artificat, use a command to generate the md5 checksum of the downloaded artifact.
      On Linux or using Cygwin on Windows, this can be done using the command "md5sum" followed by the path to the artifact.  There are also 
      programs you can download from the web to do this computation.</p>
      
      <p>Once you have the sum, go to this page at Apache: <a href="https://people.apache.org/~henkp/cgi-bin/md5.cgi">https://people.apache.org/~henkp/cgi-bin/md5.cgi</a>
        and copy / paste the generated checksum into the box.  The script on this page will then look up that
        checksum in a table it keeps for all artifacts from Apache distributions, and verify the checksum is valid.</p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection name="More details on Release Signing">
  <p>Further information on how all this works can be found at
  <a href="https://www.apache.org/dev/release-signing.html">
    https://www.apache.org/dev/release-signing.html</a></p>
  </subsection>
 </section>

</body>
</document>

