<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
distributed with this work for additional information
regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
 to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
"License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

  http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
software distributed under the License is distributed on an
"AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
specific language governing permissions and limitations
under the License.
-->

<document>
<!-- öäüÖÄÜ -->
<properties>
<title>UIMA Workshop at GSCL 2013 in Darmstadt, Germany</title>
<author email="uima-dev@apache.org">
 UIMA dev team</author>
</properties>

<body>

<section name="GSCL 2013 in Darmstadt, Germany">
<p>
The <a href="http://gscl2013.ukp.informatik.tu-darmstadt.de/de/gscl-2013/">GSCL 2013</a>,
the bi-annual conference of the German Society for Computational Linguistics and Language Technology,
hosts two UIMA-related events:
</p>
<ul>
    <li>
      <p>
        <a href="#gscl.workshop">3rd UIMA@GSCL Workshop</a>
      </p>
    </li>
    <li>
      <p>
        <a href="#gscl.tutorial">Tutorial: Natural Language Processing and Rule-based Information Extraction with UIMA</a>
      </p>
    </li>
</ul>
</section>


<section name="UIMA Workshop at GSCL 2013 in Darmstadt, Germany" id="gscl.workshop">
  
<p>
  There will be a <a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/18BfopkrOuGlhqybPf4z25_FYbA5hal7YvS7hSod4_-U/pub">workshop 
  dedicated to UIMA</a> at <a href="http://gscl2013.ukp.informatik.tu-darmstadt.de/de/gscl-2013/">GSCL 2013</a>,
  the bi-annual conference of the German Society for Computational Linguistics and Language Technology.  
  Please find the CFP below.
</p>


<p> 
<pre>
====================================================

First Call for Papers
Workshop: Unstructured Information Management Architecture (UIMA)
3rd UIMA@GSCL Workshop

September 23, 2013
Darmstadt, Germany

Further Information:
http://bit.ly/123EYSv

====================================================

In recent years, the Unstructured Information Management Architecture 
(UIMA) framework has been proposed as a middleware platform which 
offers integration by design through common type systems and
standardized communication methods for components analysing streams
of unstructured information, such as natural language. The UIMA
framework offers a solid processing infrastructure that allows
developers to concentrate on the implementation of the actual
analytics components. An increasing number of members of the NLP
community thus have adopted UIMA as a platform facilitating the
creation of reusable NLP components that can be assembled to address
different NLP tasks depending on their order, combination and
configuration.

This workshop aims at bringing together the NLP community -- users,
developers or providers of either UIMA components or UIMA-related
tools in order to explore and discuss the opportunities and 
challenges in using UIMA as a platform for modern, well-engineered
NLP. Alternatives to and comparisons of other frameworks (such as
GATE, LingPipe, etc) with UIMA are of interest, too.

Workshop topics include, but are not limited to:
- processing of very large data collections: scale-out, 
  parallelization, and performance optimization
- advanced applications driven by UIMA
- sophisticated tools to build and manage complex processing 
  pipelines
- analysis of results: exploration, evaluation, visualization, and 
  statistical analysis
- experience reports combining UIMA-based components from different 
  sources, as well as solutions to interoperability issues
- UIMA components with a special focus on genericity and type-system 
  independence
- repositories of ready-to-use UIMA-based components
- (generic) type systems for UIMA
- distribution of UIMA components: documentation, licensing and 
  packaging
- developing for UIMA: simplified APIs, debugging, unit testing, and 
  limitations of UIMA


### Submissions ###

We invite submissions of full papers, limited to 8 pages of text, and 
position papers or papers describing ongoing work as short papers, 
limited to 4 pages. Also, system demostration papers are welcome (4 
pages). Submitted paper must be original, i.e. not published in an 
earlier workshop or conference or journal. Reviewing will not be 
anonymous but authors wishing to keep their anonymity may hide their 
identity on demand. The submitted papers will be reviewed by three 
members of the program committee.

All submissions must be in English and follow the Springer LNCS style 
[1] and should be created using LaTeX. All papers must be submitted
in PDF and via EasyChair [2].

The one-day workshop will be held with oral presentations of accepted 
papers. A comfortable time slot for discussions will be given. The 
workshop will also include a keynote on Apache cTAKES, the Apache 
clinical Text Analysis and Knowledge Extraction System which is also 
based on the UIMA framework.

Note that at least one author of each accepted paper must register
and present the contribution. Accepted contributions are planned to
appear as CEUR Workshop Proceedings (CEUR-WS.org).

[1] http://www.springer.com/computer/lncs?SGWID=0-164-7-72376-0
[2] https://www.easychair.org/conferences/?conf=uimagscl2013


### Important Dates ###

July, 12:    Submission deadline
August, 16:  Notification of acceptance
August, 31:  Camera-ready deadline
Sept, 23:    Workshop held in Darmstadt in conjunction with GSCL 2013


### Organizers and Contact ###

Peter Klügl, Universität Würzburg
Richard Eckart de Castilho, TU Darmstadt
Katrin Tomanek, Averbis GmbH


Please address any inquiries regarding the workshop to: 
uima.gscl2013@gmail.com


### Program Committee ###

- Sophia Ananiadou, University of Manchester
- Steven Bethard, KU Leuven
- Ekaterina Buyko, Nuance Deutschland
- Philipp Cimiano, Universität Bielefeld
- Kevin Cohen, University of Colorado
- Anni R. Coden, Thomas J. Watson Research Center
- Richard Eckart de Castilho, TU Darmstadt
- Frank Enders, Averbis GmbH
- Nicolai Erbs, TU Darmstadt
- Stefan Geissler, TEMIS
- Thilo Götz, IBM Deutschland
- Udo Hahn, FSU Jena
- Nicolas Hernandez, University of Nantes
- Michael Herweg, IBM Deutschland
- Nancy Ide, Vassar College
- Peter Klügl, Universität Würzburg
- Eric Nyberg, Carnegie Mellon University
- Kai Simon, Averbis GmbH
- Michael Tanenblatt, Thomas J. Watson Research Center
- Martin Toepfer, Universität Würzburg
- Katrin Tomanek, Averbis GmbH
- Karin Verspoor, National ICT Australia
- Graham Wilcock, University of Helsinki
- Torsten Zesch, University of Duisburg-Essen
</pre>
</p>

</section>

<section name="Tutorial: Natural Language Processing and Rule-based Information Extraction with UIMA" id="gscl.tutorial">
  
<p>
The tutorial is split into two theoretic parts, followed by a hands-on session.
</p>
<p>
The first part gives an introduction to doing UIMA-based natural language processing 
using the <a href="http://www.ukp.tu-darmstadt.de/software/dkpro-core/">DKPro Core</a> 
component collection.  It will be shown how a processing pipeline 
can be composed from existing components, such as a tokenizer, part-of-speech tagger, and parser. 
To illustrate how such a pipeline can be used on own data and how analysis results can 
be exported to other tools, we also show how to implement simple reader and writer components. 
This includes a basic introduction to the underlying concepts, such as 
<a href="http://maven.apache.org/">Maven</a> and <a href="https://code.google.com/p/uimafit/">uimaFIT</a>.
</p>
<p>
The second part gives an introduction to <a href="https://uima.apache.org/ruta.html">Apache UIMA Ruta</a>. We will cover the syntax 
and semantics of the rule language as well as tooling support for developing rule-based 
information extraction applications.
</p>
<p>
In the hands-on session, we will implement and run a simple pipeline with DKPro Core.  
We then will extend the pipeline with rule-based post-processing in order to approach 
and solve different tasks such as information extraction. This includes solutions how 
to combine the rules with the information annotated by the DKPro components and ways for 
efficient and effective engineering of the rules themselves.
</p>
<p>
Organizers: Peter Klügl, Dr. Katrin Tomanek, Richard Eckart de Castilho
</p>
</section>

</body>
</document>

