<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
distributed with this work for additional information
regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
 to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
"License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

  https://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
software distributed under the License is distributed on an
"AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
specific language governing permissions and limitations
under the License.
-->

<document>
<!-- öäüÖÄÜ -->
<properties>
<title>UIMA Workshop at LSM 2009 in Nantes/France</title>
<author email="uima-dev@apache.org">
 UIMA dev team</author>
</properties>

<body>

<section name="UIMA Workshop at LSM 2009 in Nantes/France">
  
<p>
  There will be a <a href="https://www.uima-fr.org/RMLL-cfp.html">workshop 
  dedicated to UIMA</a> at <a href="https://2009.rmll.info/Call-for-Communication-paper.html?lang=en">LSM 2009</a>,
  the 10th Libre Software Meeting.  Please find the CFP below.
</p>


<p> 
<pre>
First French-speaking meeting around the framework Apache UIMA

Nantes, France, 8-9 July 2009
https://www.uima-fr.org/

Organized by the LINA CNRS UMR 6241 - University of Nantes
https://www.lina.univ-nantes.fr/

As part of the 10th edition of the Libre Software Meeting (LSM/RMLL)
under the conferences topic "Libre resources and software for
scientific research"
https://2009.rmll.info/Call-for-Communication-paper.html?lang=en


IMPORTANT DATES

May 29th, 2009: Intention of participation (stand for the registration)
May 29th, 2009: Paper Submission Deadline
June 3rd, 2009: Acceptance Notification
July 7-11 2009: Conference and tutorial (to determine precisely with
the LSM organizers)


OBJECTIVES

The complex nature of NLP applications -and language itself- involves
mixing different models, resources
and algorithms in the same process, leading to interoperability and
data exchange issues.

The Apache UIMA (Unstructured Information Management Architecture
https://incubator.apache.org/uima) framework offers appealing solutions
to these problems. Apache UIMA is an open, industrial-strength,
scalable and extensible platform for creating, integrating and
deploying un-(/semi-)structured information (text, audio, video...)
management applications which help to build the bridge from
unstructured information to structured knowledge. Apache UIMA
dissociates the engineering middleware problems from NLP issues, its
principles (semantic search and content analytics) are undergoing a
standardization effort at OASIS
(https://www.oasis-open.org/committees/uima/), its international
community is very active, and its Apache license fits research
objectives and allows collaboration with industrial partners.

>From 7 to 11 July 2009, the 10th edition of the LSM/RMLL (Libre
Software Meeting) will take place in Nantes, France. The LSM is an
opportunity for all sort of public (experts, beginners, professionals
or just curious people) to come together around the free software. It
is an event managed by Free, Libre and Open Source Software
users'associations from the whole country.

We would like to use this opportunity to organize a special meeting
around Apache UIMA to encourage the development of a user and
developer French-speaking community (https://www.uima-fr.org). We plan
to organize a one day meeting with both conferences and a tutorial
session. This meeting will be organized under the topic "Libre
resources and software for scientific research" of the RMLL
conferences.


TOPICS

  * Any Domain Type Systems Definition
  * Multilingual, multidocument or multi-modal analysis component development
  * Third-part tools integration
  * Natural Language and Speech Processing applications development
  * Distributed Worflow deployment and web services deployment
  * User-sensitive UIMA tools development (Graphical CAS/Worflow editor...)
  * Using UIMA as an environment for teaching NLP

We particularly wish to push forward contributions which involve
French Language processing.


INVITED SPEAKER

Pr. Udo Hahn, Head of Julie Labs (https://www.julielab.de).


SUBMISSION FORMAT

Authors may submit short papers (up to 4 pages in length). The
languages of proposal will be French or English. Please send your
submission in PDF to lsm2009@uima-fr.org with "RMLL UIMA Submission"
in the subject.
Format should follow the Springer Lecture Notes in Computer Sciences
(LNCS) templates
https://www.springer.com/computer/lncs?SGWID=0-164-7-72376-0  (For
Latex follow the Sample Latex File).
Demonstration proposals are also welcome.


ORGANISATION

LINA CNRS UMR 6241 - University of Nantes https://www.lina.univ-nantes.fr/
Contact Nicolas.Hernandez (@univ-nantes.fr)

</pre>

</p>

</section>

</body>
</document>

