<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!--
	Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
	or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
	distributed with this work for additional information
	regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
	to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
	"License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
	with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
	
	http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
	
	Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
	software distributed under the License is distributed on an
	"AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
	KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
	specific language governing permissions and limitations
	under the License.
-->

<document>

	<properties>
		<title>News</title>
		<author email="dev@uima.apache.org">
			Apache UIMA Documentation Team
		</author>
	</properties>

	<body>

		<section name="Apache UIMA News">
      <subsectionToc/>

      <subsection name="22 March 2011" date = "22 March 2011" title="Apache UIMA AS 2.3.1 released">
        <p>UIMA AS 2.3.1 is a maintenance release that contains fixes and improvements over UIMA AS 2.3.0.
        Notable updates included in this release: upgrade to ActiveMQ 5.4.1, inclusion of base UIMA 
        2.3.1 jars, improved stability and error handling, many bug fixes.
        For a complete list of bugs and improvements included in this release please see
        http://uima.apache.org/d/uima-as-2.3.1/issuesFixed/jira-report.html.
        </p>
      </subsection>
 
      <subsection name="14 February 2011" date = "14 February 2011" title="Apache UIMA underlies Watson Jeopardy! challenger">
        <a target="_blank" href="http://s.apache.org/WJ3">
          ASF news item about UIMA underlying Watson</a>
      </subsection>
      
      <subsection name="10 December 2010" date = "10 December 2010" title="Apache UIMA Java SDK 2.3.1 released">
          <p>This release only has the Apache UIMA&#0153; Java SDK, and does not yet have the other
          components.  It is backwards compatible with previous releases, except
          that Java 5 is now the minimum Java level required.</p>
          
        <p>
          This is the first release as a top level project.  
          Not many changes are in this release; included are 
          some fixes for edge cases involving Results Specification,
          a performance fix for the Component Descriptor Editor editing things having
          remote components, and several improvements to the CAS editor. 
          Please see the release notes on the <a href="downloads.cgi">downloads</a> page, for a more complete summary
          and a complete list of changes.
        </p>       
      </subsection>
      
      <subsection name="18 March 2010" date="18 March 2010" title="Apache UIMA graduates from the incubator">
        <p>
          At the ASF board meeting held on 17 March 2010, the Board unanimously approved the proposed resolution to 
          establish the Apache UIMA Project as a top level Apache project.  This signals the successful completion 
          of the incubation process and the beginning of the next phase of Apache UIMA existence.    
        </p>
        <p>
          Becoming a top level project entails setting up some new infrastructure, and moving things. 
          It will take some time to accomplish this move; in the meanwhile, we'll be keeping this website up to date.
        </p>
      </subsection>
      
      <subsection name='26 January 2010' date="26 January 2010" title="UIMA 2.3.0-incubating Released">
        <p>
          This release includes all 4 major components: 
          the UIMA Java SDK, UIMACPP, UIMA-AS (Asynchronous Scalout capability), 
          and a growing set of UIMA Addons.  It is backwards compatable with previous releases, except
          that Java 5 is now the minimum Java level required.</p>
          
          <p>
          The add-ons package contains many new components and annotators.  
          The UIMA-AS (Asynchronous Scaleout)
          framework is extensively enhanced with much more support for error/failure recovery, driven by feedback
          from actual use in several large scale deployments.  The base framework now supports Java 5 generics, and
          is enhanced to make it even more
          light-weight and efficient; for example, it now supports a new network serialization format  
          for communicating with remote
          annotators using a "delta-CAS" - limiting the response sent to just those items which have changed.
          </p>
          <p>
          Please see the release notes on the <a href="downloads.cgi">downloads</a> page, for a more complete summary
          and a complete list of changes.
        </p>       
      </subsection>     
      
      <subsection name='19 March 2009' date="19 March 2009" title="UIMA approved as an OASIS Standard">
        <p>       
          OASIS (<a href="http://www.oasis-open.org" target="_blank">http://www.oasis-open.org</a>)
          members have approved the 
          Unstructured Information Management Architecture (UIMA) version 1.0 
          as an OASIS Standard, a status that signifies the highest level of ratification. 
        </p>
        <p>See <a href="http://www.oasis-open.org/news/oasis-news-2009-03-19.php" target="_blank">http://www.oasis-open.org/news/oasis-news-2009-03-19.php</a></p>
      </subsection>     

			<subsection name='29 December 2008' date="29 December 2008" title="UIMA C++ Framework Released">
				<p>				
					The UIMA C++ Framework enables creation of UIMA compliant Analysis Engines 
					from programs written in C++, Perl, Python and Tcl. These components can be
                                        developed and tested without any Java programming.
                                        See a short introduction on <a href="doc-uimacpp-huh.html">Getting Started: UIMA C++ Framework</a>.
				</p>
			</subsection>

			<subsection name='12 August 2008' date="12 August 2008" title="UIMA CAS Editor Released">
				<p>
					UIMA Cas Editor is an annotation tool which supports manual and automatic 
					                    annotation (via running UIMA annotators) of CAS files. 
										Downloads of the project can be found on
										<a href="downloads.cgi">
											our download page.
										</a>
				</p>
			</subsection>
			
			<subsection name='24 July 2008' date="24 July 2008" title="UIMA Asynchronous Scaleout (UIMA-AS) Released">
				<p>  
					UIMA AS is the next generation scalability replacement for the Collection Processing Manager (CPM).
                                        UIMA AS provides more flexible and powerful scaleout capability, and extends support
                                        to the UIMA components not supported by the CPM,
                                        the flow controller and CAS multiplier. UIMA components can be run within UIMA AS
                                        with no code or component descriptor changes.
                                        See more on the documentation page <a href="doc-uimaas-what.html">Getting Started: UIMA Asynchronous Scaleout</a>.
				</p>
			</subsection>

			<subsection name='16 July 2008' date='16 July 2008' title='Hotfix-1 for UIMA core 2.2.2-incubating Released'>
				<p>
					This fixes memory issues with the UIMA CAS noted in 
					<a href="http://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/UIMA-1067">Jira issue 1067</a> and
					<a href="http://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/UIMA-1068">Jira issue 1068</a>.
          			The hotfix consists of one zip file, which contains a replacement for the 
          			uima-core.jar and a README with some install and usage instructions.
				</p>
			</subsection>

			<subsection name='07 May 2008' date='07 May 2008' title='Version 2.2.2-incubating Released'>
				<p>
					The Apache UIMA version 2.2.2-incubating has been released!
					For a list of all fixed issues, please refer to the 
					<a href="http://www.apache.org/dist/uima/RELEASE_NOTES-uimaj-2.2.2-incubating.html">Release Notes</a>.
					Downloads of the bugfix release can be found on
					<a href="downloads.cgi">our download page.</a>
				</p>
			</subsection>

			<subsection name='19 December 2007' date='19 December 2007' title='Version 2.2.1-incubating Released'>
				<p>
					The Apache UIMA version 2.2.1-incubating has been released!
					Downloads of the bugfix release can be found on
					<a href="downloads.cgi">
						our download page.
					</a>
				</p>
			</subsection>

			<subsection name='23 August 2007' date='23 August 2007' title='Version 2.2.0-incubating Released'>
				<p>
					Version 2.2.0-incubating has been released!
					Downloads of the project can be found on
					<a href="downloads.cgi">
						our download page.
					</a>
				</p>
			</subsection>

			<subsection name='7 April 2007' date='7 April 2007' title='Hotfix-1 for 2.1.0 Component Description Editor (CDE) Released'>
        <p>
          A "hotfix" for the Component Descriptor Editor, an Eclipse plugin used when editing UIMA descriptors,
          has been released.  This fixes functionality problems noted in 
          <a href="http://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/UIMA-364">Jira issue 364</a>.
          This hotfix consists of one zip file, which, when unzipped, constitutes a replacement for the Eclipse 
          plugin.  It includes a README-HOTFIX-1 file describing how to install it.
        </p>
      </subsection>
      
 			<subsection name='14 March 2007' date='14 March 2007' title='Version 2.1.0-incubating Released'>
				<p>
          Version 2.1.0-incubating has been released!
          Downloads of the project can be found at 
          <a href="downloads.cgi">http://uima.apache.org/downloads.cgi</a>
				</p>
			</subsection>
      
			<subsection name='20 December 2006' date='20 December 2006' title='GLDV conference workshop (Germany)'>
				<p>We are pleased announce a UIMA workshop at the <a href="http://www.sfb441.uni-tuebingen.de/gldv2007/index.en.html">GLDV 2007 spring conference</a>
				in beautiful <a href="http://www.tuebingen.de/en/1559.html">Tübingen</a>, Germany.  
				Please see the <a href="gldv07.html">full announcement</a>
				for further details.
				</p>
			</subsection>
			
			<subsection name='13 December 2006' date='13 December 2006' title='ApacheCon 2007 Europe coming up'>
				<p><a href="http://apachecon.com/2007/EU/index.html/e=MjAwNy9FVQ">ApacheCon 2007 Europe</a>
				is coming up.  We are hoping to have some UIMA attendance
				there, although we have no concrete plans as of now.  Watch this space.  If you would
				like to meet with
				UIMA folks there, drop us a line on uima-dev!
				</p>
			</subsection>
			
			<subsection name='07 December 2006' date='7 December 2006' title='UIMA Sandbox established'>
				<p> 
				  The UIMA sandbox is a workspace that is open to all UIMA committers and developers who would 
				  like to contribute code and join the UIMA developer community on Apache. Details about the 
				  sandbox can be found <a href="sandbox.html">here</a>.
				</p>
			</subsection>
			
			<subsection name='05 October 2006' date='5 October 2006' title='UIMA enters Apache Incubator'>
				<p>
				  UIMA has been accepted into the Apache Incubator by the Apache Inbubator PMC. Work begins on 
				  converting the previous code base to Apache standards.
				</p>
			</subsection>

		</section>

	</body>
</document>

